Gopal Tiwari

Bengaluru, Karnataka, India



linkedin.com/in/gopaltiwari2012



gopal.tiwari2012@gmail.com



+91 9807777735

Summary

BigData | Spark 2 | Scala | Kafka | Hadoop | Streaming | ElasticSearch | Kibana | Cassandra | Hive | Impala

Adroit Open Source and Big Data enthusiast working as Senior Software Engineer with VISA Inc., having an experience of more than 8 years in product development with Scala, Java & C#.

Advanced technical experience on ETL Big Data solutions using Apache Spark, Hadoop, Kafka, Hive, ElasticSearch, Logstash, Kibana and Cassandra. Having proclivity towards learning new technologies and languages

Having proclivity towards learning new technologies and languages. Loves exploring new languages & technologies. Always finds time to blog key ideas that I discovered while solving challenging problems.

Experience

VISA Senior Software Engineer

Visa

Oct 2018 - Present (1 year 10 months +)

Create and optimize the ETL flow to process data stored in Hive, based on the requirements from product office. Write code in Scala with Spark framework, Unit tests, and Manage git pull requests. Tuning & optimization of Spark memory & cores is one of the critical task for this project due to huge data volume ~150 Billion Records with ~6 TB on disk size.

Application Development Specialist

IQVIA

Nov 2016 - Sep 2018 (1 year 11 months)

Extracting insights from TB's of data collected at medical transactional level. Ex. Prescription adherence of a patient, his choice of medical plan, majority or plurality stores etc.

To create query builder & framework to validate, upload, schedule and process data stored in Hive, based on criteria provided in config Code is primarily written in Scala using Spark. Tuning & optimization of Spark memory & cores is one of the critical tasks for this project due to huge data volume.



Senior Systems Engineer

Infosys

Apr 2016 - Nov 2016 (8 months)

ElasticSearch, Logstash, Kibana, Kafka, Visualizations of Dashboards, Metric computation ETL coding for streaming data with Spark Streaming and Kafka. Develop Spark streaming application to show real-time metric on dashboard along with Kafka administration, extract Metric from Cassandra and Kafka, Spring Rest, Front End & Web Sockets.



Systems Engineer

Infosys

Feb 2014 - Mar 2016 (2 years 2 months)

且

Software Developer

Bizz Shine Infosystem Pvt. Ltd.

Jul 2012 - Feb 2014 (1 year 8 months)

Application development responsibilities for front-end, back-end & database development which involves technologies like ASP.NET jQuery, Bootstrap CSS, SignalR, ADO.NET and MS SQL Server.

Education



Uttar Pradesh Technical University

Bachelor of Technology (B.Tech.), Computer Science & Engineering

2008 - 2012

Graduation completed with 73% in Computer Science & Engineering, joined 4 year program in 2008 and completed in 2012.

- •Awarded honorable Mention in "International Innovative Application Competition" at Geneva, Switzerland by International Telecommunication Union (ITU), Switzerland.
- •Selected in National Level Competition-TechTop 2011 in top 18 software projects of India
- •Secured 2nd position in IBM National Software Demonstration Competition in 2012

Licenses & Certifications

MS: Programming in C# Specialist - Microsoft

MCPS: Microsoft Certified Professional - Microsoft

MS: Programming in HTML5 with JavaScript and CSS3 Specialist - Microsoft

MS: Developing ASP.NET MVC Web Applications - Microsoft

MCSA: Web Applications - Microsoft

Honors & Awards



Awarded Honorable Mention in "International Innovative Application Competition" -

International Telecommunication Union (ITU), Switzerland.

Jul 2012

Awarded honorable Mention in "International Innovative Application Competition" at Geneva, Switzerland by International Telecommunication Union (ITU), Switzerland for project Electrosoft - An Application of Software Technology for Electric Power Supply Scheduling

http://www.itu.int/ITU-T/climatechange/greenict/201206/index.html

Secured 2nd position in IBM National Software Demonstration Competition - IBM May 2012

Selected in Top 18 Software Projects of India - TechTop

Jul 2011

Selected in National Level Competition-TechTop 2011 in top 18 software projects of India.

http://www.techtop.in/

Above And Beyond - QuintilesIMS

Jul 2017

Awarded "Above & Beyond" in IQVIA for exceptional product delivery.

📕 Great Investment Idea Award - IQVIA

Sep 2017

Hackathon 2017 genomics project awarded as Great Investment Idea at IQVIA.

■ VISA Archimedes Award - VISA

Mar 2019

Honored with VISA Archimedes Award for exceptional innovations in projects.

Skills

Apache Spark • Java • Apache Kafka • Big Data • Software Development • Data Structures • Programming • Data Analysis • Data Mining • Distributed Systems